<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Prateek Sharma</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Prateek Sharma</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 11:14:19 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Audio Cloning</title>
      <link>/projects/audio-cloning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 11:14:19 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>/projects/audio-cloning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is an extension of the &lt;a href=&#34;/projects/video-translator&#34;&gt;Video Translator&lt;/a&gt; tool that generates cloned audio for short subtitles, improving the quality of audio output. The tool uses the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/myshell-ai/OpenVoice&#34;&gt;OpenVoice&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/myshell-ai/MeloTTS&#34;&gt;Melo TTS&lt;/a&gt; libraries to clone the audio output generated by the video translator tool.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Challenges faced while integrating audio cloning:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Library Compatibility&lt;/strong&gt;: The libraries were not functional on Python 3.12, which I was using. They worked on Python 3.10, so including the TTS logic in the same script was not possible.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Short Subtitles&lt;/strong&gt;: The libraries needed a longer sample audio to clone the voice better. Some of the subtitles were short, leading to errors in generating the audio for those subtitles. I cloned the OpenVoice repository and updated the checks that required longer audio samples. I also added a check to skip the subtitles that were too short.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Fixes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Video Translator</title>
      <link>/projects/video-translator/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 11:14:19 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>/projects/video-translator/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I always wished to see the Japanese anime in english. But the audio was not available in English. I had to rely on subtitles. It was the same experience while watching other foreign language movies. Constantly watching the movie and subtitles was too much hassle.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;During my break recently, I thought of exploring the possibility of translating the videos to English. With the advancement in AI and open source libraries, I decided to build a basic tool/script to achieve the same. I wanted the script to do the following:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experiences</title>
      <link>/experiences/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2025 18:53:16 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>/experiences/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;here-is-the-brief-summary-of-my-resume&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Here is the brief summary of my resume&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#here-is-the-brief-summary-of-my-resume&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lead Software Developer at Emission Critical Pvt. Ltd. (May 2022-March 2025)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Led backend development for a multi-tenant B2B SaaS platform enabling enterprise carbon footprint and sustainability tracking.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Developed and optimized carbon calculation algorithms and database queries, reducing computation time by up to 50%.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Built APIs and data pipelines for emission data ingestion, Scope 1/2/3 accounting, and supply chain tracking.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Integrated secure authentication, full-text search, and scalable architecture for emission factor management.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tech Lead at Mind Sports League (March 2021-May 2022)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2025 17:12:52 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;hello-im-prateek-sharma&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Hello, I&amp;rsquo;m Prateek Sharma!&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#hello-im-prateek-sharma&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I am a curious and passionate individual with an interest in backend development. I like exploring new technologies and learning new skills.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I started my journy in September 2014 with an online gaming company named &amp;ldquo;Adda52&amp;rdquo; as a trainee. Since then, I have worked in startups in Transport, B2B SaaS industries with team sizes ranging from 4-40+. I learnt new languages and technologies like Java, Python, Node.js, Postgres, MongoDB, Redis, and more. I have also worked with AWS, Docker and Kubernetes to deploy and manage applications in production environments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TTS Study Assistant: A Chrome Extension</title>
      <link>/projects/tts-study-assistant/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/projects/tts-study-assistant/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Introduction&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I recently built a comprehensive TTS (Text-to-Speech) Study Assistantthat enables a user to save notes, play audio for the saved notes and summarize them using AI. It combines a Chrome extension with a Go backend and React based admin panel.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;project-overview&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Project Overview&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#project-overview&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The TTS Study Assistant is a study tool that helps users:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Capture and organize notes&lt;/strong&gt; from any webpage&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Listen to text selections&lt;/strong&gt; using Chrome&amp;rsquo;s TTS API&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summarize notes&lt;/strong&gt; using AI for quick review&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Manage notes&lt;/strong&gt; using a React-based admin panel&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;architecture&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Architecture&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#architecture&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;tech-stack&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Tech Stack&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#tech-stack&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Backend (Golang)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
