<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Python on Prateek Sharma</title>
    <link>/tags/python/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Python on Prateek Sharma</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 11:14:19 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/python/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Audio Cloning</title>
      <link>/projects/audio-cloning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 11:14:19 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>/projects/audio-cloning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is an extension of the &lt;a href=&#34;/projects/video-translator&#34;&gt;Video Translator&lt;/a&gt; tool that generates cloned audio for short subtitles, improving the quality of audio output. The tool uses the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/myshell-ai/OpenVoice&#34;&gt;OpenVoice&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/myshell-ai/MeloTTS&#34;&gt;Melo TTS&lt;/a&gt; libraries to clone the audio output generated by the video translator tool.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Challenges faced while integrating audio cloning:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Library Compatibility&lt;/strong&gt;: The libraries were not functional on Python 3.12, which I was using. They worked on Python 3.10, so including the TTS logic in the same script was not possible.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Short Subtitles&lt;/strong&gt;: The libraries needed a longer sample audio to clone the voice better. Some of the subtitles were short, leading to errors in generating the audio for those subtitles. I cloned the OpenVoice repository and updated the checks that required longer audio samples. I also added a check to skip the subtitles that were too short.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Fixes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Video Translator</title>
      <link>/projects/video-translator/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 11:14:19 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>/projects/video-translator/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I always wished to see the Japanese anime in english. But the audio was not available in English. I had to rely on subtitles. It was the same experience while watching other foreign language movies. Constantly watching the movie and subtitles was too much hassle.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;During my break recently, I thought of exploring the possibility of translating the videos to English. With the advancement in AI and open source libraries, I decided to build a basic tool/script to achieve the same. I wanted the script to do the following:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
